hey folks Brett here this video is a
response to a patreon question that was
submitted by a subscriber the question
asks is there an evolutionary
explanation for the Fermi paradox or our
irrational species doom to destroy
themselves there's a problem with the
concept of irrational species any
species that exists is in some sense a
rational response to the environment
from which it has come now in our case
our species has another way in which it
can be irrational which is that we have
conscious thoughts and those conscious
thoughts can be at odds with reality but
it is really impossible to have a
species persist without it being
sensible in some deep relationship with
the universe but that actually points to
the answer to this question as well
which is it is quite possible for a
species to be in sync with its past
environment and incapable of surviving
in a future environment so the Fermi
paradox is really most likely about the
fact that if you reach a point at which
you can potentially travel and
communicate across vast distances of
space you have inevitably discovered
technologies that are capable of
creating your undoing as a species now
the question is do any species manage to
create those technologies and then not
accidentally destroy themselves quickly
thereafter my guess would be it is
possible to do especially if you are
aware enough of the problem that you can
name something like the Fermi paradox
which points to the hazard you certainly
don't need to get run over by a car to
understand why it is that you need to be
very careful walking by the curb you can
learn enough from the thought experiment
or from other people's experiences
having hit by having been hit by cars to
learn to behave safely so a species that
could recognize the hazard of
self-destruction could potentially put
safeguards in place that would negate
the hazard of the technologies that it
had invented but my guess would be it
doesn't happen very frequently that in
effect what makes populations wise is
repeated interactions with failure and
the problem is failure is not an option
once you have things like nuclear
weapons that can on leaf dynamics that
can end a species with one single error
so for Humanity the most important thing
for us to do is to recognize that even
if risks seem tolerable even if the risk
of a nuclear war occurring during any
year seems to be one in a thousand or
one in 10,000 that risk is still far too
high if our purpose is to survive in the
long term we have to find a way to get
the technologies that are capable of
destroying us under control in order for
our species to continue to persist deep
into the future hey folks if you like
this video click like subscribe to the
channel and if you feel like supporting
the creation of more content like this
head on over to my patreon page and sign
up at whatever level feels comfortable